<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The devil the greatest sinner in the world, or, A reply to Thomas Powel, who calls himself a minister of the Gospel, yet affirms, Jesus Christ was the greatest sinner in the world by John Vaughton ...</title>
            <author>Vaughton, John, 1644-1712.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1676</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V158</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1102</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12181797</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12181797</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55689</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64773)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55689)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:69)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The devil the greatest sinner in the world, or, A reply to Thomas Powel, who calls himself a minister of the Gospel, yet affirms, Jesus Christ was the greatest sinner in the world by John Vaughton ...</title>
                  <author>Vaughton, John, 1644-1712.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1676.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ.</term>
               <term>Powell, Thomas.</term>
               <term>Devil.</term>
               <term>Sin --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55689:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55689:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DEVIL THE Greateſt Sinner IN THE WORLD: Or, A REPLY to <hi>THOMAS POWEL,</hi> who calls himſelf <hi>A Miniſter of the Goſpel,</hi> yet Affirms, <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST was the Greateſt Sinner in the VVorld.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> JOHN VAUGHTON.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Lord fruſtrateth the Token of the Lyars, &amp;c.
<bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah. 44.24, 25.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>He that juſtifieth the Wicked, and he that condemneth the Juſt, even they both are Abomination to the Lord,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 17.15.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1676.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:55689:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55689:2"/>
            <head>AN Epiſtle to Thomas Powell.</head>
            <head type="sub">T. P. here follows a Copy of the Words thou gave under thy Hand, the 29th of the 2d Moneth, 1676. to J. V.</head>
            <q>
               <hi>Jeſus Chriſt was the greateſt Sinner in the World, I</hi> Thomas Powel <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel affirms.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>SInce thy giving forth of the fore-mentioned Words, thou haſt publiſh'd in print a Paper in Vindication of the aforeſaid Word<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, though thou waſt in Love ſeveral times deſired to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them before the printing of the ſaid Paper, &amp; ſo no more to have been made of them; but thou refuſing to do it, put forth thy printed Paper, as aforeſaid, to which Paper thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an Anſwer, entituled, <hi>A Vindication of Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> to which thou haſt replyed, ſtill vindicating thy former Words, <hi>viz. That Jeſus Chriſt was the greateſt Sinner in the World;</hi> In thy printed Papers thou ſay'ſt, <hi>by Imputation,</hi> but thou ſaid'ſt not ſo in thy firſt Paper. In thy Epiſtle to thy Book entituled, <hi>Mr</hi> Powell<hi>'s Anſwer, &amp;c.</hi> thou ſay'ſt, <hi>Chriſt was the greateſt of Sinners;</hi> I query of thee, whether thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveſt the Devil was not, and is not the greateſt of Sinners, he being the Original and firſt Cauſe of it, by whom it was brought into the World, and by whom it's continued and increaſed in it? I hope thou wilt not deny but that the Devil is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Sinners; and doſt thou think that the Devil muſt have no Sin imputed to him, who is the greateſt Sinner? doſt thou think he muſt bear no Puniſhment for the Sin of Mankind, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he is the Original and firſt Cauſe of it all? Conſider of this thou and the Divines of thy Way, and anſwer in Plainneſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to plain Scripture, which you profeſs to be your Rule,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55689:3"/>remember what God hath ſaid unto the Serpent or Devil, the greateſt of Sinners, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt done this, thou art curſed above all Cattel, and above every Beaſt of the Field, &amp;c.</hi> Here thou may'ſt ſee what Puniſhment God juſtly brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for leading Man and Woman into Sin; here thou may'ſt ſee how God both imputeth Sin to him, and puniſheth him for it; and thou may'ſt conſider Chriſt's Words to the Goats on the left Hand, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Go ye curſed into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels;</hi> here again thou may'ſt ſee God imputes Sin to the Devil, the greateſt of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the Original of all Sin, and not only to him, but alſo to his Diſciples, and doth and will puniſh them both for it; John 3. &amp; 8. <hi>He that committeth Sin is of the Devil, for the Devil ſinneth from the Beginning; for this Purpoſe the Son of God was manifeſted, that he might deſtroy the Works of the Devil</hi> (which is Sin) <hi>Iohn</hi> doth not ſay, he came to take the Guilt of Sin upon him, which is the Devil's Work, but ſaith, he was manifeſt to take away our Sins, and in him is no Sin; and <hi>Iohn</hi> further ſaith, <hi>In this the Children of God are manifeſt, &amp; the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Devil, whoſoever doth not Righteouſneſs is not of God, neither he that loveth not his Brother,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.10. T.P. I would have thee to conſider whether thou haſt not charged that upon Chriſt Jeſus, the immaculate Lamb of God, which is juſtly and properly to be charged upon the Devil, to wit, <hi>that he was the greateſt Sinner in the World;</hi> I could rejoyce to know thee to come out of that Spiritual Blindneſs which thou art fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to through the Deluſions of that Evil One, who certainly is the greateſt of Sinners, whatever thou or any other may think or ſay to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And in Order to convince thee of the Falſeneſs of thy Charge againſt Chriſt, to wit, <hi>That he was the greateſt ſinner in the World;</hi> I ask thee to ſhew by plain Scripture, if thou canſt, how Chriſt can be a Sinner, or the greateſt Sinner in the World, and <hi>not ſin?</hi> Sin is the Tranſgreſſion of the Law of God, Chriſt did not tranſgreſs the Law, but fulfilled it; that which renders Man a Sinner in God's Sight is the tranſgreſſing of his holy Law, which the Serpent did when he tempted the Woman to eat of the Tree, which God commanded ſhe ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55689:3"/>not eat of, he told her a Lye to encourage her to tranſgreſs God's Law, and ſhe and the Man did tranſgreſs the Law of God in eating that which God had forbidden, and thus they were lead into Sin by him, who is the greateſt of Sinners; for he became a Sinner by tranſgreſſing the Law of God, and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt Sinner, and the Original and firſt Cauſe of it in all Mankind, doth juſtly merit the Name of a Sinner, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, but the greateſt of Sinners, by Action and Imputation, and to him belongs the greateſt Puniſhment; and thus the Man and Woman came properly and juſtly to merit or deſerve the Name of Sinners, by tranſgreſſing the Law of God, &amp; to have it imputed unto them, or charged upon them, and to be judged, condemned or puniſhed for it in their impenitent and unbelieving State.</p>
            <p>T. P. take notice, that though we deny and oppoſe thy Charge againſt Chriſt, as unſcriptural and unſound, whe ſai'ſt, <hi>He waes the greateſt Sinner in the World.</hi> And in thy Epiſtle thou ſai'ſt, that <hi>the Word, He was made Sin for us, many underſtand, a Sacrifice for Sin, &amp;c.</hi> which thou ſai'ſt, thou acknowledges to be a Godly Senſe; the Godly Senſe is the true and right Senſe, which Senſe we own, and hadſt thou kept to this God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Senſe, thou had'ſt not been oppoſed by us, but thou giving another Senſe contrary to this that is an Ungodly one, and therefore we oppoſe it; yet we own that holy man Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus to be that one Offering, who hath perfected forever them who are ſanctified; I ſay, we dearly own him, who offered up himſelf through the Eternal Spirit, as a Lamb without Spot and Blemiſh; he is the Propitiation for our Sins, and not for ours only, but for the Sins of the whole World, we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Power from God the Father to preach Forgiveneſs of Sins that are paſt in the Name of Chriſt Jeſus, through the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of God: <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God which takes away the Sins of the World;</hi> be did not ſay, behold the greateſt Sinner in the World, neither did he ſay, he was g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilty of the Sins he took away And ſo <hi>T. P.</hi> and thy Brethren, keep to Scripture Language, which is a Form of found Words, which Words were given forth by the holy men, as they were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55689:4"/>by the holy Spirit of God, which Spirit gave them a right Knowledge of God and Chriſt, and led them to ſpeak right things of God and of Chriſt, which Spirit thou and thy Brethren being Strangers to, ſpeak wrong things of God and of Chriſt, and of the Scriptures alſo, for which in Love to God, Chriſt, Scriptures, and your immortal Souls, we do juſtly blame you. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>I am the Light of the World, he that followeth me ſhall not walk in Darkneſs</hi> (or Ignorance) <hi>but he ſhallhave the Light of Life; Joh.</hi> 8.12. he alſo ſaith, <hi>Believe in the Light that ye may be the Children of the Light. Joh.</hi> 12.36. We would have you to take Chriſt's Counſel, believe in the Light, and that will give you the Knoledge of God, Chriſt and the Scriptures, &amp; will lead you to ſpeak right things of God and Chriſt, and to live a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and a Chriſt like Life, and then you and we ſhall not differ.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. P.</hi> I have yet mere to ſay unto thee in Way of juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke for thy unſcriptural and ungodlike Words which thou haſt given forth in thy Epiſtle to the afore-ſaid Book, which take as followeth; thou having affirmed that Jeſus Chriſt was the greateſt Sinner in the World by Imputation, &amp;c. thou ſay'ſt, <hi>all that I ſhall urge in the defence of this great Truth is this, either Chriſt died juſtly or unjuſtly, I mean God the Father in puniſhing his Son acted therein either juſtly or unjuſtly; unjuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who dares to aſſert, juſtly, who dares to deny.</hi> &amp;c? <hi>T. P.</hi> in theſe Words laid down by thee, thou chargeſt God with puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing his Son, but how wilt thou prove it? If thou continues of this mind, I would have thee offer us ſome proof for what thou ſay'ſt, if thou canſt. which is either Scriptural or Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: By God's puniſhing his Son, I can underſtand no other by thy Words here inſerted, or any elſewhere in thy Book, then his being ſpit upon, crowned with Thorns, call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub</hi> the Prince of Devils, betrayed, murdered and hanged on a Tree.</p>
            <p>If thou ſay'ſt, this was the Puniſhment wherewith God puniſhed him, then I ask thee, who were the Inſtruments God made uſe of in inflicting theſe puniſhments upon him? Chriſt ſaid, <hi>He that dippeth his Hand with me in the Diſh, the ſame ſhall betray me; and after</hi> Judas <hi>had taken the Sop,</hi> Satan
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55689:4"/>
               <hi>entred into him,</hi> and he went to the malicious High-Prieſts and betrayed his Maſter, and they ſent a Band with Swords and Staves to take him; and as <hi>Steven</hi> ſaid, thoſe bloody High-Prieſts, <hi>Judas</hi> and the reſt of their Company were the Betrayers and Murderers of him, and they laid their wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ked Hands upon him, and crucified the Lord of Life, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.25. <hi>Him being delivered by the Determinate Counſel &amp; Fore-Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, ye have taken, and by wicked Hand, have crucified and ſlain, Acts</hi> 2.25. Now if thou charge theſe before-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Cruelties exerciſed or inflicted upon him as God's puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing his Son; will not this prove thee a <hi>Ranter</hi> in Principle at leaſt? for doſt thou not hereby juſtifie the Devil and all his bloody Train to be God's Servants, and Doers of God's Wiill herein; for I have heard, that ſome of the rude Ranters have ſaid, that the Devil is God's good Servant; &amp; what doſt thou ſay leſs? for if all theſe Cruelties be eſteemed PRINCIPALLY God's Act, it's eaſie to prove from Scripture, that the Devil and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men did inflict thoſe Cruelties upon him; Chriſt told that bloody Generation, <hi>They were of their Father the Devil, and the Luſts</hi> (or Works) <hi>of their Father they would do, he was a Lyar and a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>derer from the Beginning;</hi> here thou may'ſt ſee that Chriſt told this bloody Crew, <hi>That the Luſts</hi> (or Works) <hi>of their Father they would do,</hi> which Luſts (or Works) was Lying and Murder; Chriſt did not tell them, that their lying and murdering of him were the Works of God, or his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Son, but that they were of their Father the Devil. Thou ſay'ſt in the ſame Page, <hi>Chriſt may thank Sin for all his Sufferings, &amp;c.</hi> If ſo, then he might thank the Devil, who is the Author of it (but he i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not worthy of Thanks) this is ſome of thy dark divining.</p>
            <p>There is another Thing I am not willing to omit, that is in the ſame page; thou ſayeſt. That <hi>Sin ſet the Father againſt Chriſt:</hi> It may be thou may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt call this a <hi>Theſis,</hi> but it is a dark one; it may be thou mayeſt ſay, <hi>It's D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>try, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>are a Silly Ignorant People, and do not underſtand it;</hi> but come <hi>Tho. Powel,</hi> thou ſayeſt, <hi>Scripturs is thy Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſhew us plain Scripture for it, if thou can'ſt; for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Quakers</hi> love
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55689:5"/>Scripture very well, and God hath given them the Knowledge of them, and Comfort of them by the Holy Spirit, by which the holy Men were moved to give them forth; Glory to his holy Name for the ſame, and for all his Bleſſings and Mercies. Now Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The Father hath not loft me alone; for I do alwayes thoſe things that pleaſe him,</hi> John 28.29. and the Father ſaith of the Son, <hi>This is my Beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed, hear ye him,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.17. <hi>T. P.</hi> I deſire thou mayeſt believe the Father and the Son's Teſtimony before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned, and Repent of thy dark and unſcriptural Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. P.</hi> There is one more dark unſcriptural Saying of thine, which I muſt rebuke thee for; thou ſayeſt in the ſame page of thy <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> the words are, viz. <hi>Chriſt was accounted a Sinner by Wicked Men; but that is not all, he was accounted alſo a Sinner by his Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this Poſition or Affirmation thou holdeſt forth, that God and Wicked Men are of one Mind (which never was or can be) Wicked Men ſay, <hi>He caſt out Devils by Beel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub;</hi> and ſaid, <hi>Say we not well, thou art a</hi> Samaritan, <hi>and haſt a Devil?</hi> And Wicked Men told the Blind Man, whoſe Eyes Chriſt opened, <hi>Chriſt was a Sinner;</hi> and thou ſayeſt, <hi>God accounted him alſo a Sinner, or elſe</hi> (ſayeſt thou) <hi>he would not have dealt ſo ſeverely with him as he did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>T. P.</hi> This is written in Love and Rebuke to thee; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that its written, <hi>The Rebukes of a Friend are better then the Kiſſes of an Enemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Feild.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="essay">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55689:5"/>
            <head>THE DEVIL THE Greateſt Sinner IN THE WORLD.</head>
            <p>THat <hi>Thomas Powel</hi> ſhould call his Pamphlet, <hi>An An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to</hi> John Vaughton <hi>and</hi> John Field, <hi>their Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pamphlet,</hi> as he doth falſly ſtile it in his Title<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, I might indeed very much admire, but that I do find him grown to a very great height of Confidence or Impudence [that he hath ſaid, <hi>That he is ſatisfied, that neither</hi> Chriſtians <hi>nor his Aequaintance will give Credit to any thing that the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>ſhould ſay of him,</hi> pag. 1.] A notorious Untruth indeed; for many, both <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and his Acquaintance do believe, That what the <hi>Quakers</hi> have ſaid of him is true, and he himſelf is made to confeſs to much of it, as hereafter I ſhall make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and notwithſtanding he doth find fault with that Account that I have given of that Diſcourſe that paſt between <hi>T. P.</hi> and my ſelf, which Account given by me I ſhall ſtand by; and I could have added ſomething more, that at that time paſſed between us, which might have tended further to the manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Folly, but I did not at that time think it material to the Controverſie, that was then and is ſtill between us; but inaſmuch as he hath undertaken to give forth a Narrative, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55689:6"/>to tell his Reader <hi>its a True One</hi> (when indeed much of it is falſe, and its much ſhort of giving an Account of much of our Proceedings, and the Fairneſs of our Dealings to him is omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) but ſuch is the Practice of many, who would aſſume to themſelves the Name of <hi>Goſpel. Miniſters,</hi> and pretend to the People, that Scripture is their Rule, and the only Rule of Eaith and Practice; and when we call to them for plain Scripture, for the proving of their Doctrine (though ſo fundamental that they confide in it, and upon it lay the whole ſtreſs of their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation) we cannot obtain it; but inſtead thereof they give us their dark Meanings and feigned (humble Conceivings) and their Hopes (though vain) that its according to it, as this my Adverſary hath done, who hath paſſed over much of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Paſſages of my Book, and hath taken no notice of them, and yet, as I ſaid before, calls his Pamphlet an Anſwer to it; for Proof whereof I refer my Reader to the 8th page of my Book, which is as followeth; <q>But <hi>Thomas Powel</hi> having now in print declared, that he meant by Imputation, then we muſt read his words thus, <hi>I</hi> Thomas Powell <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel affirms, Jeſus Chriſt was the Greateſt Sinner in the World (by Imputation)</hi> Now <hi>T. P.</hi> with the reſt of the Divines of thy Way, give us plain Scripture that ſaith, Jeſus Chriſt was by <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> or any of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, affirmed to be the Greateſt Sinner in the World by Imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and give us plain Scripture that ſaith, He took the Guilt of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ins upon him: for though it is ſaid <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. That <hi>he laid upon him the Iniquity of us all;</hi> or as the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word hath it, <hi>He made the Iniquity of us all to meet on him;</hi> or as in the 10th Verſe it is ſaid, <hi>He was made an Offering for Sin;</hi> it doth not ſay, he was gulity of Sin. Now T. P. give us plain Scripture that ſaith, Jeſus Chriſt by taking, bearing or ſuffering for Sinners, that he became guilty of Sin, and that he was the Greateſt of Sinners; and give us a plain Scripture that ſaith, He hath more Sins to anſwer for then any particular Sinner: For although I have read of the Sins of <hi>David,</hi> whom I ſuppoſe you do believe was an Elect Perſon, whoſe Sins were (as in Scripture recorded) Murder and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55689:6"/>yet I do not find by any Teſtimony of Scripture, that Jeſus Chriſt was guilty of <hi>David</hi>'s Sins, nor of <hi>Paul</hi>'s Sins, who was a Perſecutor of him in his Members; nor of <hi>Peter</hi>'s Sin, who denyed him. And T. P. I query with thee, Whether thou be an Elect Perſon, or nay? if yea, then tell me, whether Jeſus Chriſt be guilty of thy Lyes, ſome of which are hereafter mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> T.P. affirmed, <hi>That he had writ the word Imputation;</hi> but the Original being ſhewed, his Lye appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and then he ſaid, he had writ the word <hi>Imputation,</hi> but that <hi>John Vaughton</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Note. <hi>After</hi> T. P. <hi>had writ Jeſus Chriſt was the greateſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the World, and had laid the Paper by, and after ſeveral words more had paſt between us, he ſaid,</hi> God made the Devil, <hi>and I gave him the ſame Paper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and in it he writ,</hi> God gave the Devil his Being. <hi>And of this I have Witneſs.</hi>
                  </note> ſnacht his Paper from him; and this alſo was and is teſtified to be a Lye.</q>
            </p>
            <p>So much of my Book, and more that might be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he hath not taken notice of it, and it ſtandeth over his Head.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall proceed to clear my ſelf from the Lyes that he would caſt upon me (for they are his and not mine) I ſhall begin with the firſt that he charges me with, which is in the 2d. page of his Book; his Words are theſe, <hi>If</hi> J. Vaughton <hi>had been a Chriſtian he would have done like a Chriſtian,</hi> i. e. <hi>done me right by acquainting the World, that though</hi> Thomas Bye <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied the Word Imputation, as ſpoken by me before, yet he denied not but that it was ſpoken by me juſt after it was written.</hi> Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is not <hi>T. P.</hi> in a paſſion thinks thou or void of Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, firſt to note me as a Liar, and then to query whether I am a Chriſtian or no, and at another time to conclude me to be none, and to charge me with doing him wrong, becauſe I did not tell the World that he ſpoke the Word <hi>Imputation</hi> after he had written, when he had told the World himſelf, and had brought his Witneſs to prove it, a thing that I did not in my Book contradict, that which I contradicted him for was his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55689:7"/>ſaying, that he mentioned the Word <hi>Imputation</hi> before he gave me thoſe Words under his Hand, viz. <hi>Ieſus Chriſt was the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Sinner in the World, I</hi> Thomas Powel <hi>Miniſter of the Goſpel affirms;</hi> ſo that his ſaying, and bringing his Witneſs to prove that he ſpoke the Word <hi>Imoutation</hi> before, was and is a Lye, and for his ſaying, he can produce the Original under <hi>T. B</hi>'s Hand, but this neither proves the Words true, nor <hi>I. Vaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> a Liar, as <hi>T. P.</hi> would have it, who after all his Buſle doth confeſs, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at his Witneſs having called to Mind cannot remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>T. P.</hi> had the Word <hi>Imputation</hi> before, but for all this <hi>T. P.</hi> makes a great Noiſe, and in page 3. ſaith, that he doth not ſay poſitively he had it not, and counts <hi>Iohn Vaug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton</hi> as <hi>a flagitious Relator;</hi> what his Witneſs now ſaith is not the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but what his witneſs did then confeſs and acknowledge, that is it I related in the 8th page of my Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, i. e. Thomas Powel <hi>did not ſpeak nor mention the Word</hi> Imputation <hi>before he wrote thoſe Words:</hi> Now if this be not a poſitive Aſſertion tell me what is one, and then let me know whether thou haſt not abus'd me in accounting me a flagitious Relater, and thy Witneſs alſo, by getting deſiring or procuring him who cannot read writing to ſubſcribe as a Witneſs to that which he cannot call to mind, will this evidence paſs or be taken by any that's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciencious? but this is <hi>T. P</hi>'s. Witneſs ſtill, who indeed hath ſaid, he is not willing to have <hi>T. Powel</hi> run down, but he will help him what he can, though to little purpoſe, except it be to enſnare himſelf: So its evident the Lie is between <hi>T. Powel</hi> and his witneſs, and I am clear of it, but <hi>T. P.</hi> ſaith, to clear him from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie <hi>(a thing he would not be guilty on for a World)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him who will, I cannot ſo long as I can trace him in them, but <hi>T. P.</hi> ſaid, that <hi>T. B.</hi> ſaid <hi>to clear him (though he could not remember the Word</hi> Imputation <hi>before, yet he gave him his Hand freely and voluntarily</hi> The greater is his wickedneſs, if it be ſo, and he muſt bear his Burden. <hi>Another Lie of</hi> John Vaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's, as he falſly terms it is in the 9th page of my Book where in I make uſe of <hi>William Farrinton</hi>'s Name, telling my Reader that he ſaid, T. P. <hi>was a Liar, and that he had told many Lies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it;</hi> though <hi>Thomas Powel</hi> counts this a Lie, and ſaith
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55689:7"/>William Farrinton <hi>denieth it,</hi> yet I can prove it by a witneſs who heard him ſpeak it, and <hi>William Farrinton</hi> ſince hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it under his Hand that T. P. <hi>hath ſpoken ſome <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruths a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it;</hi> I would have this Equivocater to tell me what Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence there is between an Untruth and a Lye; but he ſaith, that <hi>William Farrinton</hi> ſaid, <hi>If he knew him to be a Liar</hi> (which I queſtion not but he doth) <hi>yet he would not have told ſuch as the</hi> Quakers. What he means by ſuch, I need not much inquire, but that he hath ſince T. P's Book was written, told the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> that <hi>T. P. had ſpoken divers <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruths about it,</hi> ſo that I ſhall ſtill note <hi>T. P.</hi> for a L— The third thing that he charges upon me as a Lye, is no Lye of mine; the matter is this, <hi>That W. F. upon ſight of what T. P. had written,</hi> ſaid <hi>he would not ſtand by his Words for</hi> 10000. <hi>Worlds, and that he ſhould not preach in his Meeting-Houſe till he had publickly condemned it;</hi> did he publickly condemn it before he preacht? no ſuch matter, then no Lye of mine; but he ſaith,
<note place="margin">Note. <hi>And</hi> W. F. <hi>in whoſe mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting houſe he preacht, did when he had done, ſtand up and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd what T. P. brought in Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Doctrine out of</hi> Luther.</note> that <hi>I know that he condemned it in a Sermon;</hi> He might be aſhamed of his Confiidence, if he is not paſt it; for inſtead of condemning it, he told the People, <hi>he hoped he had proved that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelical Doctrine, which was, that Jeſus Chriſt was the greateſt Sinner in the World, as he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;</hi> the People at that time being deſired to turn to their proof to ſee whether he had done it, many anſwered No, nor never could; but T. P. tells me, <hi>he doth now condemn it, as I in my Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance take it,</hi> page 4. viz. <hi>That he was a Sinner Actually.</hi> Why Ignorance? It's Blaſphemy to affirm that Chriſt Jeſus was a Sinner by Action or Imputation; for though wicked men did ſay Chriſt was a Sinner, yet they could not convince him of Sin; and God doth not impute Chriſt a Sinner, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver committed Sin, and Chriſt cannot juſtly be imputed a Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner except he had committed Sin; for he only is a Sinner that committeth Sin, which Chriſt never did, therefore no Sinner by Action nor Imputation in God's account; for it is evident,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55689:8"/>that Sinners are out of a converted eſtate, and are in Error, as in <hi>James</hi> 5.20. <hi>Let him know that he that converteth a Sinner from the Error of his Way, ſhall ſave a Soul from Death, &amp;c.</hi> but Chriſt Jeſus was never in Error, &amp; therefore no Sinner; for God is holy and pure forever, and Chriſt Jeſus is the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Father's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. It is ſaid <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.14. <hi>Chriſt came not to call the Righteous, but Sinners to Repentance;</hi> if Chriſt was the greateſt Sinner in the World, as <hi>T. P.</hi> hath affirmed, then the greateſt Sinner calls the leſſer to Repentance, which is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. Again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. <hi>God commended his Love to us in that whileſt we were yet Sinners, Chriſt died for us.</hi> If Chriſt Jeſus was the greateſt Sinner in the World, as <hi>T. P.</hi> hath affirmed, then the greateſt Sinner died for the leſſer, which is contrary to the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi>'s Teſtimony, as it's recorded in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Chriſt alſo hath ſuffered for Sin, the Juſt for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt, that he might bring many to God.</hi> Again, <hi>James</hi> 4.8. <hi>Cleanſe your Hands ye Sinners, and purifie your Hearts ye double minded:</hi> So that by this Scripture it doth alſo appear, that SINNERS are in an unclean Eſtate, and have need of cleanſing, and if the leſſer Sinners have Need, much more the greateſt, for ſo T.P. hath affirmed Chriſt Jeſus was: And though he calls himſelf <hi>a Minſter of the Goſpel,</hi> yet is he an Enemy to God and Chriſt, alſo a Contradicter of plain Scripture Teſtimony; and ſuch is his Wickedneſs againſt us, that when we have given our Belief of Chriſt Jeſus, and have confeſſed unto him in all his Manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both within and without, in plain Words, ſuch as our Adverſary confeſſes in themſelves good, <hi>yet unſavourily,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>ſmells a</hi> Quakers <hi>Rat in them,</hi> and he doth alſo avouch, <hi>That all we ſay concerning Chriſt without is but a meer Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, vide</hi> page 10. of T. P<hi>'s</hi> Book; and yet our Adverſaries do confeſs, though to the Contradiction of themſelves, that it is but a reaſonable Thing for Perſons to give their own Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to their own Words; but this reaſonable Thing we have not yet obtained from them. <hi>The fourth Lye he charges</hi> John Vaughton <hi>with is, his denying the</hi> Quakers <hi>to be no</hi> Chriſtians: The <hi>Quakers</hi> are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and Chriſt is the hope of their Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55689:8"/>and J. V. no Lyar in denying the contrary; and T. P. ſaith, <hi>the</hi> Quakers <hi>have been proved no</hi> Chriſtians, that I deny, except ſuch <hi>Quakers</hi> as have been of the Forger's making: And for his terming <hi>Thomas Hicks</hi> an ingenuous Man for undertaking to prove the <hi>Quakers</hi> Hetrodox, both in Principle and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, is a vain Floriſh and an empty Boaſt; for in undertaking that Work he has procured himſelf a Name that will certainly render him odious to Poſterity; and for his Pains and Labour therein, he ſhall certainly have his Reward with the Lyars and Maker of Lyes in the Lake that burns with Fire and Brimſtone, except he repent: But why doth T. P. ſay we are DUMB is it not becauſe he is in Conſuſion; for he tells his Reader, that we drowned him with our Voice, and T. H. may give him the Lye herein, for doth he not know that the <hi>Quakers</hi> Voice hath been loud enough to prove him a Perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a Lyar and a Forger. The fifth Lye he charges me with is, <hi>my denying that to be our Principle, which</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>we have ſo often declared,</hi> viz. <hi>Chriſt dyed only as an Example;</hi> I deny that it is our Principle, or that we have often declared that Chriſt died only as an Example; for we do own (and ever did) that Jeſus Chriſt was an Offering or a Sacrifice for Sin, <hi>And he is the Propitiation for our Sins, and not for ours only, but for the Sins of the whole World,</hi> 1 John 2.2.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>T. P</hi>'s ſaying, <hi>That the</hi> Quakers <hi>are conſcious to themſelves, that they are no</hi> Chriſtians, is ſurely a Lye of his own coyning.</p>
            <p>Now having cleared my ſelf from his Lyes, which he would have made mine, I ſhall take a little notice of his Paſſage, wherein he tells his Reader, <hi>He ſhall make him Smile,</hi> by which thoſe that are ſerious may ſee what Spirit this Man is of, who ſcoffs at <hi>Revelation,</hi> and makes ado about my going (as he ſaith) into the Country when he was at <hi>London,</hi> and there was neither Preacher nor People. Now I declare, and that in Truth, That at that time I went into the Country to a Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Friends, and I being told that it was T. P's Day to be there, according to his uſunl manner, and having Time e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough before our Meeting to go to his Meeting, I did go, not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55689:9"/>upon Revelation after that manner as he would inſinnate, but upon the Information, as I had before; and when I came to his Meeting, I was told that he altered his Day on that day I was there before, whether it was to prevent my meeting with him or not, I ſhall leave: &amp; I do ſay, that we do not place our going to enquire for a Place or Perſon upon Immediate Revelation. And I ſhall refer my Reader to that Paſſage of his to his Reader, that ſaith, <hi>They made us who were a great People, to deſert our Place,</hi> whether we met with him and his People or no: So that I have good Cauſe ſtill to truſt in the Revelation of God's Power, which did not only confound and drive him away from diſturbing
<note n="‖" place="margin">Note. T. P. <hi>came into his Meeting when I was ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the People in the Fear of God, and the People were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſtill; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he came in, he endeavoured to ſtir up the Bad, but the Lord's Power was with us, and</hi> T. P. <hi>went away, and took the rougheſt of the People with him, &amp; then we had a Peaceable and a Quiet Meeting for about Three Hours, and though he tells his Reader,</hi> That we were ſo rude, that one would have thought that we came out of a Bear-Garden. Yet I ſay, <hi>this is a great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth, for ſuch Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour was not on our Parts, who were ſober, and kept in God's Fear, and to Scriptural Expreſſions, but on thine, whoſe ſaying to one of us, when at thy Meeting, was,</hi> Sirrah, come down; <hi>which I am ſure ſavours more of a</hi> Bear Garden <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, then of a Miniſter's of Chriſt Jeſus. And thou further ſaidſt at that time, and in thy Book ſince avoucheſt,</hi> That we deſerve to be whiped, ſcourged, and put in the Stocks; <hi>by which people may ſee, was thy Power as great as thy Will, that Whipping, Scourging, and putting us in the Stocks ſhould be the Weapons or Arguments that thou wouldſt uſe inſtead of the Sword of the Spirit, which is the Word of God and true Miniſters Weapons) So that its manifeſt, that a Meaſure of the old perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting ſpirit, that ever was a Mark of the falſe Church and her Miniſters, hath entred thee; but thy Horn is too ſhort. We were ſober, and kept in God's Fear, and the Rudeneſs was with him, and thoſe that followed him, of whom I do ſay, Except they come to Repent, and turn from the Evil of their Doings, they cannot lay down their Heads in Peace:</hi> For it is not every one that cryes Lord, Lord, ſhall enter the Kingdom of Heaven; but he that doth the Will of my Father which is in Heaven.</note> of us, and hindring the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony which God had put into our Hearts that day, but alſo ſetled the minds of the greateſt number of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Hearts of many were ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; and I hope the Senſe that a Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant had of God's immediate Power, will be as an Engagement for them to wait daily for to feel the ſame, that ſo their Hearts may be engaged unto the Lord, and that his Fear may be ever pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in their Hearts, that they may know him to be to them as a Fountain of Life, to keep them from the Snares of Death.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55689:9"/>
            <p>And for <hi>Thomas Powell</hi>'s Railing againſt me, and calling me <hi>Falſe Prophet,</hi> and pronouncing me accurſed, and ſuch like Expreſſions, comes from the Heat of his Spirit, and ſo may juſtly be reckoned amongſt his Bed-ridden Performances, and his Fly-blown Duties, as he calls them, <hi>which Phraſes</hi> (he ſayes) <hi>Chriſtians underſtand very well.</hi> I would have <hi>T. P.</hi> to tell me, Whether the Spirit of God leads to ſuch Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Duties, or the ſpirit of Satan? And mayſt not thou be aſhamed to take Money of People for ſuch Duties and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances? Well, God's Hand is againſt thee and thy Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; and it had been better for thee to have ſtood ſtill, as I have formerly told thee, and to have known God's Salvation, and his Power to have kept thee from venting forth ſuch Bed-ridden and Fly blown Stuff; and if thy beſt Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces be ſuch, what is the worſt?</p>
            <p>And <hi>T. P.</hi> in his 5th Page ſaith, <hi>He ſhall firſt conſider the Title of my Book, which is this, A Vindication of Jeſus Chriſt, the Immaculate Lamb of God. Note,</hi> He leaves out what I vindicate him from, which was from the Foul and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Imputation of one <hi>Thomas Powell,</hi> a Preacher among the <hi>Independ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nts,</hi> who affirmed,
<note n="*" place="margin">Note, <hi>It was not a Poſition, as he would inſinuate; but it was an Affirmation.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt was the Greateſt Sinner in the World;</hi> he takes no notice of it, as though it concerned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55689:10"/>him not, and yet he calls his Book an <hi>Anſwer</hi> to mine; furely he ſtill perſiſts in Lying, notwithſtanding I warned him to the contrary.</p>
            <p>But he goes on, and ſayes, <hi>He admires at my Confidence, to ſtile my Book A Vindication of Chriſt Jeſus; if I had not been a</hi> Quaker (he ſayes) <hi>it had been ſomething.</hi> What! is it nothing now? or, is it become a Crime for a <hi>Quaker</hi> to vindicate Chriſt Jeſus from ſuch foul and blaſphemous Expreſſions, as he hath uttered? and is his admiring at it, and his ſaying, <hi>He cannot believe it,</hi> and calling my Title but a <hi>Pretence,</hi> and a <hi>Bait to catch poor Souls, a ſufficient thing to prove it ſo?</hi> But it is no Wonder why the Man is grown to ſuch a Degree of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulity as to believe after this rate, ſeeing he excludes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any Dependency on Chriſt within, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> own him; and how do the <hi>Quakers</hi> own him as to his inward Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance? To be <hi>the True Light that Lighteth every man that cometh into the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>T. P.</hi> ſayes, <hi>We ſay we own every Principle of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an-Religion.</hi> Is that become a Crime in this pretended Miniſter's Account? Its very probable it is ſo; for he tells his Reader, <hi>That our owning Chriſt, or any other Principle of Religion, to be a meer Myſtical Romance;</hi> and <hi>that we own ſuch a Chriſt as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt's Chriſt;</hi> ſuch kind of Stuff and Matter as its like he has learned from <hi>Thomas Hicks</hi> the <hi>Forger</hi> (and the reſt of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) he communicates to his Reader, inſtead of bringing plain Scripture to clear himſelf from his ſoul and blaſphemous Charge of Sin to Chriſt. I need not much enlarge to prove we own Chriſt Jeſus, or our ſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſeeing it never entred into the Hearts, nor was ever the Doctrine of any of the <hi>Leading-Quakers,</hi> as he terms them, to Deny Chriſt Jeſus in any of his Appearances or Manifeſtations, whether within or without; and though Men in their prejudiced Spirits do judge us as <hi>Denyers of Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> Yet be it known unto all, That we expect Salvation and Redemption by no other Thing or Means whatſoever, then by that Chriſt Jeſus declared of and born witneſs unto in the Holy Scriptures: But if our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and men of corrupt Minds, who are ſatisfied in their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55689:10"/>Bed-ridden Performances, and their Duties Fly-blown with Sin cannot believe us, be it known unto them, That we never did go about to impoſe a Belief upon any without inward Conviction; but we ſtill did and do commit our Teſtimony to the Witneſs of God in the Conſciences of all men, knowing <hi>that it is God only that can perſwade the Hearts of men and Women to love the Truth, and to walk in Subjection thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing I ſhall take notice of is in the 6th page of my Adverſary's Book, his words are theſe; <hi>They acknowledge ſuch a Chriſt as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſts Chriſt;</hi> for his Proof he hath theſe words, <hi>They deny him to be God Man in one Perſon, they deny him to be a Diſtinct Perſon from the Perſon of the Father, and they deny him alſo to be a Diſtinct Perſon from any of his Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We own God, the man Chriſt Jeſus, by whom God will judge the Secrets of all Hearts, and the true Unity and Fellowſhip, as they owned them that writ the Scriptures, howbeit we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, both that Chriſt after the Fleſh was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> yet is God over all bleſſed forever, that the Father is greater then the Son, and yet one; and that Chriſt is Head and Lord of his People, yet one with his People; but for <hi>T. P</hi>'s School-Diſtinctions, and School-Gibberiſh we ſhall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves therewith; for his Words are not according to the Form of ſound Words laid down in the Scripture, yet he pretends the Scripture to be his Rule.</p>
            <p>If any deſire further Satisfaction concerning us in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter above hinted at, they may peruſe theſe Books entituled, <hi>The Divinity of Chriſt aſſerted; The Chriſtian-Quaker;</hi> and <hi>Quakeriſm a new Nick Name for old Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for his ſaying, that <hi>it had been better for me to have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled my Book,</hi> No Chriſt but Conſcience; <hi>and in this,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>thou wouldſt have been true to thy principle.</hi> Here's a notorious Untruth; for we never preacht ſuch a Chriſt as could be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ſin; but Conſcience may be defiled, and may be ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and if this be his State, Wo and miſery will be his Portion, notwithſtanding his Imagination of Chriſt's Righteouſneſs to be his, and his Sin Chriſt's. And to proceed he ſaith and avou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55689:11"/>that <hi>the Diſcourſe between us, ſave a paſſage or two was feigned,</hi> page 6. of his Pamphlet; in which he ſaith, <hi>I relate this as our greeting one another,</hi> i. e. <hi>you</hi> Quakers <hi>hold damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and erroneous Doctrines;</hi> And to prove him a L — in this I refer my Reader to the 3d page of my Book, and the Title of that part of the Diſcourſe which paſſed between us; my words are theſe, <hi>Something of a Diſcourſe,</hi> &amp;c. not all, nor yet our greeting; for he having formerly given me a Book, wherein he pretends he diſcourſed the Devil? and that he had almoſt perſwaded him to believe he was the true God; the thing ſeemed to be fictious; but however, I asked him, whether the thing was real? and whether he had ſeen the Devil? if he had, after what manner? he ſaid, <hi>He was cloathed with black like a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster;</hi> I queried, how he knew that he was the Devil? he ſaid, he <hi>asked him whether he created the Heavens and the Earth; and he ſaid,</hi> Yea, and you too; <hi>by this</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I knew him to be the Devil:</hi> my anſwer to him was this, how doth this prove him to be the Devil? for he that did create the Heavens and Earth, and gave man Life, Breath and Being was and is the true God; but <hi>T.</hi> P. ſaid, <hi>He told me alſo, that him whom I and the greateſt part of the World worſhipped was not the true God, and by this alſo I knew him to be the Devil:</hi> How doth this prove him to be the Devil? waſt not thou at that time in Diſtraction? he ſaid, <hi>he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> then ſaid I, thou couldſt not worſhip the true God; for a man muſt firſt know him before he can worſhip him; &amp; then he in his Fierceneſs breaks forth and ſaid, <hi>You</hi> Quakers <hi>hold damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and erroneous Doctrines:</hi> And though he ſaith, <hi>the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is fictious both in its Dependency, and in its Matter;</hi> yet I do affirm, that the Diſcourſe that paſt between us, his Queſtions and my Anſwers, and my Queſtions and his Anſwers are placed in my Book according as they were ſpoken; and if I had done otherwiſe, it had been ſomewhat like that notable Forger <hi>Tho. Hicks,</hi> a man ſo much in his Eſteem for his Dexterity in ſuch matters, that he counted him <hi>a Divine</hi> in the preſence of the People at his Meeting in <hi>Hartford</hi> Shire; but T. H. gives him the Lye, and in plain Words ſaid, <hi>I am no Divine;</hi> if T. P. thinks that I have placed this paſſage of T. H. and his upon my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55689:11"/>Memory only, he will be miſtaken; for I have it, and much more of that dayes work in writing from divers Perſons who took it in ſhort Hand from their Mouths.</p>
            <p>One thing more I ſhall take notice of, that is, his telling his Reader, <hi>He durſt not enter into Diſputation with us on the Lord's Day,</hi> yet notwithſtanding he ſends me a Challenge to meet him (on that Day he calls the Lords Day) and procures <hi>T. Hieks</hi> to help him; the Words of his Chalenge I thought meet to inſert, to the End that his Brethren might ſee what Attempts this late upſtart Preacher, though in vain, doth make, who threatned, with one more, in one day, <hi>to ſhake our Foundation quite down,</hi> which is more then all his Brethren have, could, or ever ſhall do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The Words of <hi>Thomas Powel</hi>'s Challenge are, viz.</p>
            <p>John Vaughton, <hi>I expect thee for to make good what thou haſt fathered up on me next Sabbath Day at my Meeting in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; I ſhall be ſure to be there, and another with me, where I with him ſhall ſhake your Foundation quite down; for it is ſandy, and I perceive you are upon your laſt Legs already; this day I go into the Country, being the</hi> 31. <hi>of</hi> Auguſt <hi>to prepare my ſelf for expelling that Soul-damning Doctrine which thou haſt vented in the poor Country; thy Friend</hi> Tho. Powel.</p>
            <p>By this People may ſee the notorious Falſneſs of this man, who challenges me into the Gountry, &amp; yet would inſinuate into his Reader, that we aſſaulted him, dog'd him, and followed him into all places, when I can truly ſay, that ſince this Controverſie hath depended between us, that neither I, nor the Friends concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with me, have followed him into no other place but publick Meetings; but the Spirit of <hi>Cain</hi> having entred him, from whence his Fear comes, which makes him to ſay, <hi>he dare not go alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you Divines of his way conſider, whether <hi>Tho. Powel</hi> be a Goſpel-Miniſter, or a falſe Prophet, and (take his own Phraſe) <hi>run on the Devil's Errand?</hi> But for our Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it ſtands ſure, notwithſtanding his Attempts, and the <hi>Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſher</hi>'s too.</p>
            <p>I have alſo taken Notice of a Marginal Note in Page 6. of his Book, his Words are theſe, <hi>Reader, if thou believeſt that
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55689:12"/>this Diſcourſe paſſed between</hi> J. V. <hi>and my ſelf, thou muſt value his Memory at an high Rate; but I am apt to think that his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory is as fallible as yours and mine, though he had the Confidence to tell me that he was perfect:</hi> A Forger indeed, I never told <hi>Tho. Powel</hi> that I was perfect; he would inſinuate into his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the Diſcourſe was feigned, from his Suppoſition of the Fallibility of my Memory, his Thoughts of the Fallibleneſs of my Memory is no Proof of the Diſcourſe feigned; and for the Fallibility of his Memory I have an Inſtance, that he ſaid, I told him I was perfect, which Words he never had from my Mouth; for we preach not our ſelves, but Chriſt Jeſus; and the Doctrine of Perfection is the Doctrine of Chriſt, and they that oppoſe it are Anti-chriſt, and the State of Sanctification, through the Spirit of God, I do believe is attainable on this Side the Grave; for I do declare that I have no Faith in the <hi>Papist Purgatory,</hi> though our Adverſaries number us amongſt them: And in page 7. he notes me for a Lyar, in ſaying he ſaid, <hi>Burn the Bible;</hi> hear his Proof. <hi>Mr</hi> Bye <hi>my Witneſs doth alſo atteſt, that as far as he remembers, I ſaid no ſuch Word, but away with the Bible, which was the Words I ſpoke, I very well remember.</hi> Muſt the fallible Memories of <hi>T. P.</hi> and his Witneſs go for a Proof, and I from thence termed a Lyar; no ſuch Matter, for I have a Witneſs that heard, and can very well remember that <hi>T. P.</hi> ſaid, <hi>Burn the Bible</hi> more then once or twice. And in page 10. he avoucheth, <hi>That one of the</hi> Quakers <hi>Principles is, that all except themſelves ſhall be confounded and damned;</hi> this he brings for the Vindication of his former Aſſertion that he had given in the Name of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> in Anſwer to a young Man that put this Query, <hi>Seeing you are but a People of about</hi> 25 <hi>Years ſtanding, and you ſay that your Way is the right Way, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of the People that dyed before you were a People? they</hi> (ſaid <hi>T. P.) believe they are all damned;</hi> This he would not have imputed to his Envy and Malice, but to his Judgment, <hi>and that Judgment</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>is grounded from an underiable Conſequence, that reſulteth from ſeveral Phraſes ſcattered up and down in their own Books;</hi> one that he mentions is this, <hi>that their Way is the only Way;</hi> Now how doth this prove, that our Saying <hi>Chriſt Our
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55689:12"/>Way is the only Way,</hi> to be determined as our Belief, that all that dyed before we were a People are damned? for we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Way of God, which is but one, was in all Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that there was a Remnant that walked in this Way, and found Acceptance with him, and this Way was and is Chriſt, who is the true Light that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World, and this Light is not Conſcience (as he would wickedly inſinuate) but it ſhines in the Hearts and Conſciences of all the Sons and Daughters of Men, to diſcover and make manifeſt thoſe Things that are Evil; and they that receive it in this its Manifeſtation, come to know the Power and Sufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of him who ſaid, <hi>I am the Light of the World, he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves in me ſhall not abide in Darkneſs, but ſhall have the Light of Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And my Adverſary talks of ſeveral <hi>Quakers</hi> Books, yet he ſayes, <hi>He hath but one</hi> Quakers <hi>Book in his Study,</hi> i. e. <hi>a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm of</hi> G. F. <hi>and</hi> (he ſayes) <hi>it's to his Purpoſe,</hi> he quotes it thus, <q>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Father, Are <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> that do not believe in the Light, that which doth enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en every Man that cometh into the World, all out of him who is the Life, the Light of Men? Anſwer, <hi>Yea Child:</hi>
               </q> From theſe Words this paſſionate Man falls a railing, and ſayes, <hi>It's a Helliſh Book, and that the Principles contained in</hi> G. F<hi>'s Catechiſm are Principles that the Devil in Hell hath hatched;</hi> ergo, <hi>Soul-damning Principles.</hi> Principles that are of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's making, or hatching, as he phraſes it, are Soul damning; but that <hi>G. F's</hi> Words are of the Devil's hatching, that I deny; for they are in themſelves ſafe and ſure; for how can People be in him, <hi>i. e.</hi> Chriſt the Light, that lighteth every Man that cometh into the World, and not believe in him? and if not in him, then out of him; and this is no wayes to his Purpoſe (as he ſaid it was) to prove that we believe that all were damned that were before we were a People, or that our Principles are Soul-damning: And now I come to my Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary perfect Confirmation of his Aſſertion (as he calls it) which ſeems to be very fictious; but however hear it, page 8. he ſaith, <hi>For a perfect Confirmation of my Aſſertion,</hi> viz.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55689:13"/>
               <hi>That the</hi> Quakers <hi>do hold, that all who dye not in Belief of their Principles ſhall be damned; ſee in this enſuing Relation that I ſhall ſtand by; Once a Maiden-Acquaintance of mine was courted by a zealous</hi> Quaker, <hi>who during the Time he was Suitor, had prevailed with her to go with him to hear his Friends, ſcil.</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>and that once or twice; at laſt he demandeth of her how ſhe liked them? ſhe anſwered worſe and worſe, which occaſioned him to break off from her, and withall to ſay, that if ſhe heard any other, ſhe would certainly be damned.</hi> Would <hi>T. P.</hi> and his Brethren have their Faith and Principles be concluded and determined Damnable from the Words of one Man? Certainly no, and that ſuch an one as they have not ſo much as the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Name; but this is perfect Confirmation (as he calls it) not to mention his imperfect Ones) But I ſhall at this Time leave it amongſt his Fly-blown Stuff. And he tells his Reader, <hi>He hath preached almoſt three Years for only Charges defrayed:</hi> But I may take Leave to tell him, that that doth not clear him from preaching for what he could get; but if his Charges were ſo great every time he went into the Country, as it was that Day he met with the Country-Prieſt he told me of, and two of his Companions at a Tavern, where after their Friendſhip, threatned to kill him for preaching againſt the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts;</hi> and as they were going to have him to the Place of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, which was upon a Bed he having about five Pounds in his Pocket, as he himſelf related, it tumbled out, of which he ſaid, <hi>It was as the Ram that appeared for the ſaving of</hi> Iſaac, <hi>to ſave him from being executed by them;</hi> for after they perceived his Money, they conſulted and agreed to ſave his Life; but it may be ſuppoſed, if this Story of his be true, that he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo much of the Vintner's ſweet Wine that he was not in his Right Senſes; for he alſo ſaid, <hi>They put him into a Coach, and ſet him down at the Stocks Market</hi> London, <hi>and that he knows not the Perſons, Tavern nor Street where this thing was done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To his Reader I take notice of theſe Paſſages, where he ſaith, viz. <hi>The Father accounted Chriſt a Sinner — and that the Father puniſhed his Son, or inflicted Puniſhment upon his Son—Sin
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55689:13"/>ſet the Father againſt Chriſt—that Chriſt's Sufferings are penal—God the Father puniſhing his Son—and that Chriſt ſuffered juſtly.</hi> For theſe Sayings, I deſire thee, or any of thy Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines to give me plain Scripture for, ſeeing you call it your Rule; and give us no more your Corrupt Meanings upon it, neither your Feigned Humble Conceiving, nor Vain Imagination, but let it be plain Scripture it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Here follows ſome of T. P's <hi>brief ſeaſonable, ſoul-affectionate</hi> and <hi>good Advice,</hi> as he calls it, <hi>unto the Principal Leaders of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>&amp;c. O profligate flagitious Wretches! that muſt imbrue your Hands in the Blood of Souls, that you cannot go to Hell alone, but you muſt have Company with you—O ye Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgaters of Errors—Leaders of a great many to Hell, &amp;c.</hi> This with much more Stuff that is fly-blown with Sin, as he ſaith his Holy Duties are, who alſo ſayes, <hi>Our Books have Croaking Toads, and Creaking Vipers, that ſwarms therein, &amp;c.</hi> Which Expreſſions of his ſavour more of Railing <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhekah</hi>'s ſpirit, then of the Meek Spirit of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomas Powell,</hi> thou in thy <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> having deſired us to clear our ſelves from thoſe notorious <hi>Lyes</hi> and <hi>Forgeries</hi> that thou haſt charged us with; I have done it, and do return them upon thee and thy Witneſs, with the reſt of thy <hi>Confederates,</hi> to whom they do belong.</p>
            <p>And <hi>T. P.</hi> as to the <hi>Promiſe</hi> that <hi>Thomas Hicks</hi> hath made thee, it will be unſafe for thee to give Credit to it, or to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide in it; for that which he hath promiſed thee is a Work too ponderous for him, to wit, to prove the <hi>Quakers No Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and their Religion a Cheat;</hi> for <hi>Gog</hi> and all his great Army cannot do it. Moreover, <hi>Thomas Hicks</hi> of all men ſhould ceaſe boaſting of what Help he will miniſter to thee or others, ſeeing he hath undertaken more Work of his own already, then himſelf or any other that he has brought for his Aſſiſtance could perform; the <hi>Task</hi> he hath already undertaken lieth ſtill at <hi>kis Door.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN VAUGHTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:55689:14"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>CHriſt Jeſus was the Father's free Gift, as it is ſaid, <hi>God ſo loved the World, that he gave his only begotten Son a Light into the World, that whoſoever bolieveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have Everlaſting Life;</hi> ſo that Chriſt Jeſus was not bound or forced, for ſaith he, <hi>I lay down my Life freely;</hi> ſo that it was his free Love; and will the Profeſſors now, after all their ſeeming &amp; pretended Love to him, brand him with being guilty of their Sins? Well, we do ſay, he is not guilty of any man's Sin, but hath all power in Heaven and Earth-committed unto him, and can pardon Sin without being guilty of it, and is the Lamb of God that taketh away the Sins of the World; and the Father hath committed this Power unto him, and he doth not charge his Son with the guilt of the World's Sins; therefore T. P. and the reſt of the Divines of thy Way, repent of your Evil, and of all your hard Speeches which you have uttered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Spotleſs Lamb of God, and thoſe that follow him in the Regeneration, and content not your ſelves in ſaying, <hi>your Sins are imputed Chriſt's, and his Righteouſneſs imputed yours,</hi> whileſt you are in the Act of Sin and Rebelling againſt his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for this Covering, or vain talking will be too ſhort in the Day of the Lord, that haſtens to be revealed againſt all Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Men, who hold the Truth in Unrighteouſneſs, or make a Profeſſion of Chriſt the Truth, and live ſtill in the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs, and in the Sin, and in Rebellion againſt God's Light and Spirit, which, makes Sin manifeſt, and reproves for it in the very Heart, where Sin hath been and is committed; and this Light many of you have been calling with many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious Names and Terms, for which you muſt repent, or elſe you cannot lay down your Heads in Peace, that is the Word of Truth unto you all, whether you will hear or forbear.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John Vaught<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="testimony">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:55689:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Thomas Firth</hi>'s Teſtimony to the Truth of ſo much of the Diſcourſe that paſt between <hi>Thomas Powell</hi> and <hi>John Vaughton,</hi> as was printed in <hi>J. V</hi>'s Book Entituled, <hi>A Vindication of Chriſt Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>WHereas</hi> Thomas Powel <hi>relates,</hi> That the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in the aforeſaid Book was Feigned or Fictious, ſave a Paſſage or two; <hi>I, who was an Eye and Ear-Witneſs, do affirm it to be True, as it is there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated and I have Unity with the publiſhing of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas Firth.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
